Dallapiccola/Dwight Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Dallapiccola/Dwight Collection1951-1989 (bulk 1951-1975)
ML31.D33
Dallapiccola, Luigi, 1904-1975
around 750 items 13 boxes 8 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Luigi Dallappiccola was an Italian composer. The collection contains Dallapiccola's correspondence with Peggie Dwight, including over 300 letters (written mostly in French) and various postcards and telegrams. In addition, there are over 200 articles and programs relating to Dallapiccola's career, mostly collected during those years. The collection also includes a few of Dallapiccola's holograph music manuscripts, most notably his opera Ulysses, as well as short excerpts or sketches of his works. There are also printed editions of two full scores for Requiescant and Sex Carmina Alcaei.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Dallapiccola, Luigi, 1904-1975--Autographs.; Dallapiccola, Luigi, 1904-1975--Correspondence.; Dallapiccola, Luigi, 1904-1975.; Dallapiccola, Luigi, 1904-1975.; Dallapiccola, Luigi, 1904-1975. Ulisse.; Dwight, Margaret--Correspondence.; Dwight, Margaret.; Dwight, Margaret. Dallapiccola/Dwight collection. 1951-1989.
Subjects
Composers--Italy--Correspondence.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift; Margaret Dwight; January 1990.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Transfers
An audio tape was transferred to the Library of Congress Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division.
Access and Restrictions
Commentary prepared by the donor and all correspondence are sealed until 2025 or until the death of Luigi Dallapiccola's daughter Annalibera. The rest of the Dallapiccola/Dwight Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Performing Arts Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use. Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Sketch
Luigi Dallapiccola was born in Italy on February 3, 1904. During his youth, Dallapiccola gained diplomas in both piano and composition from the Cherubini Conservatory in Florence. He began his career as a piano teacher at the Conservatory, where he remained until his retirement in 1967. He also taught music courses at several American colleges and summer music programs.
As a composer, Dallapiccola was greatly influenced by the music of the 2nd Viennese School, evident in his use of serial methods. His output encompassed dramatic works (operas and ballet) as well as choral, solo vocal and instrumental compositions. Several of his vocal works were considered to be "protest pieces," relating to his ever-present concern with the political situations of his time.
Margaret (Peggie) Dwight is an American artist currently living in Paris. She had a correspondence with Dallapiccola from the time she met him at Tanglewood in 1951 where she was a student, until his death in 1975.
Scope and Content Note
The bulk of this collection represents Dallapiccola's correspondence with Margaret (Peggie) Dwight during the years of their association, from 1951 to 1975. This correspondence includes over 300 letters (written mostly in French), as well as various postcards and telegrams. In addition, there are over two hundred articles and programs relating to Dallapiccola's career, mostly collected during those years.
The collection also includes a few of Dallapiccola's holograph music manuscripts, most notably his opera Ulysses, as well as short excerpts or sketches of his works. Printed editions of two full scores are included, namely Requiescant and Sex Carmina Alcaei.
The writings in this collection consist mainly of 200 pages of "Recollections" written by Margaret (Peggie) Dwight which chronicles her 24-year friendship with Dallapiccola. It is divided into sections by year, and contains references to various letters and other materials in the collection. There are also several speeches and other miscellaneous notes written by Dallapiccola.
Organization of the Dallapiccola/Dwight Collection
The Dallapiccola/Dwight Collection is organized in 7 series:
Correspondence
Music
Programs & Clippings
Writings
Photographs
Books
Miscellaneous
http://lccn.loc.gov/2003561020
Container List
- Correspondence, 1951-1974 (Box 1-3)
  Correspondence with Margaret (Peggie) Dwight during the years of their association, from 1951 to 1975. This correspondence includes over 300 letters (written mostly in French), as well as various postcards and telegrams. Please note: access may be restricted, refer to "Access and Restrictions" in the Administrative Information section for additional information.
  Arranged chronologically by date
  - 1951-1958 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - 1960 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - 1961 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - 1962 Jan.-Aug. (Box-folder 1/4)
  - 1962 Sept.-Oct. (Box-folder 1/5)
  - 1963 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - 1964 Jan.-July (Box-folder 1/7)
  - 1964 Aug.-Dec. (Box-folder 1/8)
  - 1965 Jan.-Apr. (Box-folder 1/9)
  - 1965 May-Dec. (Box-folder 1/10)
  - 1966 Jan.-May (Box-folder 2/1)
  - 1966 June-Dec. (Box-folder 2/2)
  - 1967 Jan.-May (Box-folder 2/3)
  - 1967 June-July (Box-folder 2/4)
  - 1967 Aug.-Dec. (Box-folder 2/5)
  - 1968 Jan.-July (Box-folder 2/6)
  - 1968 Aug.-Dec. (Box-folder 2/7)
  - 1969 Jan.-June (Box-folder 2/8)
  - 1969 July-Dec. (Box-folder 2/9)
  - 1970 Jan.-May (Box-folder 3/1)
  - 1970 June-Dec. (Box-folder 3/2)
  - 1971 Jan.-July (Box-folder 3/3)
  - 1971 Aug.-Dec. (Box-folder 3/4)
  - 1972 Jan.-Apr. (Box-folder 3/5)
  - 1972 May-Dec. (Box-folder 3/6)
  - 1973 Jan.-June (Box-folder 3/7)
  - 1973 July-Dec. (Box-folder 3/8)
  - 1974 Jan.-1975 Feb. (Box-folder 3/9)
- Music, 1943-1970 (Box-folder 4/1-14, Box-folder 12/1-2)
  Holographs of Dallapiccola music manuscripts, short excerpts or sketches, and printed editions.
  Arranged by title.
  - Cinque Canti, Song no. 4, 1956, Holograph full score in pencil, [5 p.] (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Commiato, 1972, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil, 10 p. (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Requiescant, Milan, Zerboni, 1958, Printed full score, 57 p. (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Requiescant, Milan, Zerboni, 1958, Printed, piano-vocal score, autographed, 47 p. (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Sex Carmina Alcaei, Milan, Zerboni, 1943, Printed full score, 32 p. (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Sicut Umbra, sketch, (1969-70), Holograph ms. in pencil, [2 p.] (Box-folder 4/5)
  - [Sketch leaf, 1956], Holograph ms. in pencil, [1 p.] (Box-folder 4/12)
  - [Sketchbook 1957-58], Bound holograph sketches in pencil, [22 p.]; Includes Requiescent and Ulysses (Box-folder 4/13)
  - [Sketches, 1968], Holograph ms. in pencil, [2 p.]; Includes Ulysses and Michaelangelo the Younger (Box-folder 4/14)
  - 12-Tone Demonstration, sketch See also: "Recollections" p. 45, Holograph ms. in ink, [1 p.] (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Ulysses, Act I scene 3, sketches, 1968, Holograph ms. in pencil and ink, [2 p.] (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Ulysses, Act II scene 3, 1967, Holograph condensed score in pencil, [10 p.] (Box-folder 4/8)
  - Ulysses, Calypso scene, sketch, Holograph piano-vocal score in ink, [1 p.] (Box-folder 4/9)
  - Ulysses, Nausica Scene, 1966, Holograph condensed score in ink, [2 p.] (Box-folder 4/10)
  - Ulysses, Scene de l'Enfer, 1962, Holograph score in pencil, [2 p.] (Box-folder 4/11)
  - Ulysses, Act I, 1966, Holograph full score in ink, autographed, [1 p.] (Box-folder 12/1)
  - Ulysses, Prologue, Calypso Scene, sketch, 1968, Holograph condensed score in pencil, [2 p.] (Box-folder 12/2)
- Programs & Clippings, 1951-1989 (Box-folder 12/3, Box 5-9)
  Programs and clippings of Dallapiccola.
  - 1951-59 (Box-folder 5/1)
  - 1960 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - 1961 Jan.-Feb. (Box-folder 5/3)
  - 1961 Mar.-Dec. (Box-folder 5/4)
  - 1962 (Box-folder 5/5)
  - 1963 (Box-folder 5/6)
  - 1964 Jan.-Oct. (Box-folder 6/1)
  - 1964 Aug.-Oct. (Box-folder 6/2)
  - 1964 Nov.-Dec. (Box-folder 6/3)
  - 1965 (Box-folder 6/4)
  - 1966 (Box-folder 6/5)
  - 1966 May 5th (Box-folder 12/3)
  - 1967 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - 1968 Mar.-Aug. (Box-folder 7/1)
  - 1968 Sept. (Box-folder 7/2)
  - 1968 Oct.-Dec. (Box-folder 7/3)
  - 1969 Feb.-Aug. (Box-folder 7/4)
  - 1969 Oct.-Dec. (Box-folder 7/5)
  - 1970 (Box-folder 7/6)
  - 1971 (Box-folder 7/7)
  - 1972 (Box-folder 8/1)
  - 1973-74 (Box-folder 8/2)
  - 1975 (Box-folder 8/3)
  - 1975, Obituaries (Box-folder 8/4)
  - 1976-79 (Box-folder 8/5)
  - 1980-82 (Box-folder 8/6)
  - 1984-89 (Box-folder 8/7)
- Writings, 1951-1976 (Box-folder 10/2-5, Box-folder 14/1, Box 9)
  The writings in this collection consist mainly of 200 pages of "Recollections" written by Margaret (Peggie) Dwight which chronicles her 24-year friendship with Dallapiccola. Please note: access may be restricted, refer to "Access and Restrictions" in the Administrative Information section for additional information.
  Arranged into two subseries by author and chronologically.
  - Writings by Margaret (Peggie) Dwight (Box-folder 14/1, Box 9)
    - Recollections, 1951-58, p. 1-28 (Box-folder 9/1)
    - Recollections, 1959-61, p. 29-55 (Box-folder 9/2)
    - Recollections, 1962-63, p. 56-84 (Box-folder 9/3)
    - Recollections, 1963-65, p. 85-117 (Box-folder 9/4)
    - Recollections, 1966-67, p. 118-156 (Box-folder 9/5)
    - Recollections, 1968-70, p. 157-201 (Box-folder 9/6)
    - Recollections, 1971-76, p. 202-end (Box-folder 9/7)
    - Recollections, Notes, 8 p. (Box-folder 9/8)
    - Collection contents list, [2 p.] (Box-folder 9/8)
    - Recollections (revised), 227 p. (Box-folder 14/1)
  - Writings by Luigi Dallapiccola (Box-folder 10/2-5)
    Libretti and notes by Dallapiccola
    Arranged by title
    - Lecture, L. Dallapiccola, "Birth of Libretto," 25 p. (Box-folder 10/2)
    - L. Dallapiccola, "Ulysses," typed libretto, 24 p. (Box-folder 10/3)
    - L. Dallapiccola, Notes, Includes "Goethe Lieder," "Greek Songs" and "Prisoner," [5 p.] (Box-folder 10/4)
    - L. Dallapiccola, Misc. Notes, [2 p.] (Box-folder 10/5)
- Photographs (Box-folder 11/3)
  Photographic prints of Ulysses production dated 1968.
  Arrangement is by subject.
  - Ulysses. Photographs, Berlin production, 1968 (Box-folder 11/3)
- Books (Box-folder 10/1)
  Book by Franco Nencini
  Arranged by author
  - Nencini, Franco
    - Firenze i giorni del diluvio (Box-folder 10/1)
- Miscellaneous (Box-folder 11/1-2, Box-folder 11/4, Box-folder 13/1)
  Miscellaneous materials
  Arranged by format
  - McDonald, Calum; Luigi Dallapiccola, A Complete Catalogue, 21 p. (Box-folder 11/1)
  - Program, New York Philharmonic, April 29, 1936, Autographed by Arturo Toscanini (Box-folder 11/2)
  - Champagne cork, autographed, 1969 (Box-folder 11/4)
  - Poster, 1979, Concert in honor of Dallapiccola given by Maggio Musicale, Florence (Box-folder 13/1)